They ask me Who are you by nation I say
меня спрашивают Кто ты по нация Я говорю
I am a Circassian And who are the Circassians Well I say
Я черкес А кто такие черкесы Ну я говорю
Kabardian And we know the Kabardians Well
кабардин а кабардинцев мы знаем э
Kabardian There is no such nation There are
кабардинец нету такой нации есть
correct to say Circassian from Kabarda Yes
правильные сказать черкес с кабарды Да
that would be more correct But nobody
это будет правильней но черкесов никто
knows the Circassians Our history was destroyed Forgive
не знает нашу историю уничтожили Извини
me We are with the Russians  fought for how many two
меня Мы с русскими воевали сколько два
decades almost
десятка почти
100 years there was almost a war from above
лет 100 лет было там почти война свыше
and Salam aleikum where are you from brother Vaaleikum
а Салам алейкум ты откуда брат Ваалейкум
salam
салам
Circassian Circassian adik psu who I am Circassian And
черкес черкес адык псу кто Я черкес А у
my father is
меня отец
Circassian Natu what
черкес нату что
Natuhai my father is from Shapsug
натухай у меня из шапсуга
Sugi And where do you live now
суги А ты сейчас где живёшь
Tyumen Yes right now  our Circassians are scattered
Тюмень Да сечас черкесов наших раскидало
all over the world from Jordan to all yes you know
по миру от Иордании до всё да ты знаешь
that the king of Jordan has Circassians as his guards yes
что у короля Иордании охрана черкесы да
there are purely our Circassians Yes 60% of the guards
Там чисто наши черкесы Да 60% охраны
in short and the army Even even in Turkey 67%
короче и армии Даже даже в Турции 67%
in short Circassians are warriors yes ours  there are
короче черкесы воины да наши
more Circassians in Turkey than Circassians in
черкесов в Турции больше чем черкеса в
Russia now Because when the
России сейчас Потому что когда
Russian Empire
Российская империя
came to the Caucasus How many of our
пришла на Кавказ Да сколько изгнал наших
brothers were expelled Yes, 90% of us were destroyed here in
братьев Да нас же уничтожили здесь в
Russia
России 90%
Yes, I know When I am now in Estonia I
да я зна Я когда я сейчас в Эсто Я в
live in Estonia, it turns out my father Under the
Эстонии живу у меня получается отец При
Soviet  In the Union I came to Estonia and there I
Советском Союзе приехал в Эстонию и там
married an Estonian mother and stayed there I am
женился на маме эстонки и остался там я
half Estonian half Shapsug and
наполовину эстонец наполовину шапсуг и я
when I come across
когда вот попадаются мне в чат рулетки с
these Russians from the Krasnodar region in the chat roulette Yes I
Краснодарского края эти русские Да я
say they are there I say And what does
говорю они там вот я говорю А что
Sochi mean in Russian What does
означает по-русски Сочи Что означает
Gelendzhik mean  chimita Quad Yes what Adler what are
Геленджик чимита Квад Да что Адлер какие
these Russian words why is it not
это слова русские почему оно не
called mud there Vnukovo Yes they are
называется грязево там Внуково Да они
like that because Great Circassia
такие потому что Великая Черкесия аж до
was all the way to Crimea to Crimea back and
Крыма была до Крыма обратно та
Krasnodar Stavropol Krai is the land of
Краснодарский Ставрополь край это земли
Circassian Circassians Circassians yes
черкесова черкесов черкесов да
saber Yes saber is a Circassian word yes
шашка Да шашка это Черкесское слово да
Well Duma
Ну Дума
what  yes, the Cossacks, yes, the Cossacks,
что да казаки типа да так казаки
in their clothes  look at those Cossacks who were
при одежда смотри те казаки которые были
once in Ukraine, they don't look
когда-то в Украине они ж не так выглядят
like these Kuban Cossacks. Yes, they took everything
как вот эти кубански Да они взяли всё
Circassian, they took
Черкесское взяли
dad, they even took dancing, towards the end, they
папа танцы даже взяли уже под конец уже
took dancing, they took
танцы взяли
Sasha, in short, they took the saber, everything, and
там Сашку короче ну шашку взяли всё а
then they say it's like an extension of the hand. This is
потом говорят как продолжение руки Это
long.  dagger
длинный кинджал
Yes, when I meet them they start talking
Да я когда встречаю они начинают говорит
about there were these wild tribes running around bosses and
о там эти дикие племена бегали боссы и
naked Yes, they all So, damn, they themselves wore bast
голые Да они все Значит сами блин в
shoes they wore bast shoes even before the 10th century
лаптях ходили они ещё до X века в лаптях
look
ходили посмотри
I tell the Russians look Circassian
Я говорю русским посмотри Черкесский
folk costume and Russian folk
народный костюм и русский народный
costume Circassian folk costume My God
костюм Черкесский народный костюм Боже
beauty is Russian there is no Russian
красота есть русский нет русского
national costume a bag a bag on
народного костюма мешок мешок на
some kind of put on and that's it That
какой-то на себя надевали и всё Вот и
was the whole costume Yes if in reality we take
был костюм весь Да если в натуре взять
history in short in reality and national
историю короче в натуре и национальный
costume of some kind there
костюм какой никакого не
was none Ukrainians have Belarusians have Estonians have
было украинцев есть у белорусов есть у
we have  the Russians have no Circassians, they
эстонцев у нас есть у черкесов есть у
don't have them and they never have had them,
русских нету нету и не было
the saber was also renamed as
никогда шашку тоже переименовали как
if everyone thinks it's a kaza. Forgive
будто все думают что это каза Извини
me  and the Cossacks Who were the
меня а казаки Кто такие там были
meetings there were they were not Russians there was a
собрания это не русские были там было
meeting everyone was there and Caucasians were there
собрание все там и кавказцы были там
Tatars and Mongols yes warriors warriors yes
татары и монголы да воины воины были да
warriors even the same Ermak take his
воины даже того же Ермака взять его
real name turns out not Ermak
настоящее имя оказывается не Ермак
Arme he was a Turk Turk Turk well there
Арме он тюрок был тюрок тюрок ну
was an uprising  Yes, many are against the kingdom
восстание было ж Да против царства
Many ask in short they
многие Многие спрашивают короче
talk Yes, who are you by nationality In short,
разговаривают Да ты кто по нации Короче
I say I am a Circassian And who are the Circassians yes yes yes
я говорю Я черкес А кто такие черкесы
everyone knows the Chechens Circassians Nobody
дадада чеченцев все знают черкесов Никто
knows we Circassians fought until the
не знает мы черкесы воевали до
last we How many years did we
последнего мы Сколько лет мы Египтом
rule Egypt 600 years Yes when did you because
правили 600 лет Да когда лю потому что
the Russians destroyed  this story
русские уничтожили эту историю
[ __ ] this is Obi of course you know how
бля это Оби конечно знаешь как вот
look you take a book the history of Russia but
смотри берёшь книжка история России да
there is no word about the Caucasian peoples
там нет слова про кавказские народы как
how Russia was everything and then they came and
вот была Россия всё а потом пришли и
conquered and something appeared there And
завоевали и что-то там появилось А
listen uh Even if you look Well these are
слушай ээ Вон даже если смотреть Ну это
not Circassians but uh  where is the avar derbent 5.000
не черкесы а ээ где аварца Дербент 5.000
years of the city of Derbent you understand the Caucasus historical When in Russia there was still cold snow in the Caucasus there was a sea and all the empires All in short civilizations were intertwined there and take history even This Russian This writer writes in short I forgot how he is now I will not say when the Tatar-Mongols like went to Rus' and they conquered like there Rus' but they couldn't conquer Rus' because they couldn't get through the Circassians and that's why there's only two lines about Rus' because there Take a take War they stopped there Tatar-Mongols They couldn't get through there war neither war nor Adyghe how could they Well Muscovy there well maybe there was something shorter and then they didn't fight they just took Yes they withered and fought hells and Wars of Russian history pono Well nobody knows Circassians You saw They were last year I I also watched some guy from Cherkessk, uh, he spoke and said that the Russians took and hung up a billboard with Yermolov's billboard  Cherkessky with
билборд с ермоловы билборд Черкесский с
Yermolov, can you imagine who
ермоловы представляешь который геноцид
committed the genocide of the Circassians? Yes, they hanged him, but
черкесов делал Да повесили но бегом
after the noise they took him down on the run. They are these
после шума сняли бегом сняли Они же эти
cunning ones, they make these various Russian
хитрые они делают эти всякие русские
communities. And they are engaged in banditry. And
общины Да и бандитизмом занимаются Да и
they say if you know, if some guy is
говорят если знаешь если какой-то парень
like a Caucasian
типа там кавка
at the Armed Forces, he is a bandit and
у ВС э банди и
yes  And how many Russians kill each other and it's
да А сколько русски убивает друг друга и
just awful How many children do they have
ужас просто Детей своих Сколько у них
Yes son
Да сын
mother something about this like Katz
маму об этом что-то как Кац кого-то
you know someone Russian like when like
русского знаешь ка когда типа
sy is it normal when an athlete is from the
сы это нормально когда спортсмен с
Caucasus Yes he plays for Russia they are
Кавказа Да выступает за Россия они вот
this is a Russian
это российский
athlete yes everything  with the flag all this is our
спортсмен да всё с флагом всё это наш
Russian Well done look how a
российский Молодец смотрите как
Russian athlete when somewhere someone
российский спортсмен когда где-то кто-то
fight Oh these mountain peoples Yes there
драка О вот эти горские народы Да там
it is popry exit exit izd kavka persons of
это попри выход выход изд кавка лица
Caucasian nationality yet Yes how
кавказской национальности ещё Да как
only they they don't even understand
только они ж они же даже не разбираются
what is there  there are Circassians, there are
да что есть там есть черкесы есть э
Vainakhs, there are Avars, many people
вайнахи есть там аварцы они многие про
think that Dagestan is some kind of place
Дагестан думают что там какие-то
Dagestanis live they don't know there are
дагестанцы живут они не знаешь там кумы
some kind of godfathers there ba sarands Avars Lezgins
какие-то ба саранды аварцы лезгины
Rutuls Dargins
рутульцы даргинцы
40% I when I tell Yes to Russians Yes for
40% я я когда рассказываю Да русским Да
example that they are what Kabarda there
например что вот они что Кабарда там
for example Adyghe Yes it was all Circassians
например Адыги Да это всё черкесы было
yes that Lenin specially divided it so
да что Ленин специально так разделили
that they would be in different republics
чтобы по разным республикам были
you know so that we weren't all Circassians
понимаешь чтобы не были черкесы все
together yes we all kind of in general
вместе да мы все как бы в общем нас
called us Circassians it's the
черкесами называли это по-моему
English I think or the French in short
англичане по-моему то ли французы короче
Travelers in short yeah and Many of
Путешественники короче угу и Многие даже
ours don't even know young people for example who are from
наши не знают молодые например кто с
Kabarda and they ask me Who are you  by
кабарды и у меня спрашивают на Кто ты по
nation I say I am a Circassian And who are
нация Я говорю Я черкес А кто такие
the Circassians Well I say Kabardin And
черкесы Ну я говорю кабардин а
we know the Kabardins Well Kabardins There is no
кабардинцев мы знаем э кабардинец нету
such nation It is more correct to say
такой нации есть правильнее сказать
Circassian
черке
SRD That would be more correct But
срд это будет правильнее но черкесов
no one destroyed the Circassians Our history Forgive
никто не нашу историю уничтожили Извини
me We fought with the Russians For almost two
меня Мы с русскими воевали сколько два
decades  100 years there was almost a war there more than
лет 100 лет было там почти война свыше
100 more than
100 свыше
100 I already so in short where many
100 Я так уже короче де много
generations of us even had a discussion with
поколений сес даже дискуссия была с
Kadyrov
Кадыровым
ours not ours in short he himself is a Dagestani
наш не наш короче он сам дагестанец
in my opinion Well he is a very strong historian
по-моему Ну он историк очень сильный
now I can't say he
сейчас не смогу сказать он Кадырову
tells Kadyrov we
говорит мы
Circassians fought to the last  not a single
черкесы воевали до последнего ни один
Circassian surrendered to the Russians in short and you
черкес не сдался русскому короче а вы
Chechens say you survived Imam Shamil
чеченцы говорит сохранились Имам Шамиль
your survived He surrendered not a single
ваш сохранился Он сдался в плен ни один
Circassian
черкес в плен не
surrendered Imam Shamil at all he Oh even
сдался Имам Шамиль вообще он О даже
more than that Imam Shamil was an Avar the
больше того Имам Шамиль аварец был у
Chechens did not have Avari Imam Shamil was
чеченцев не было авари Имам Шамиль был
their
ихним
leader Yes  and even Zelensky also
лидером Да и даже вот Зеленский тоже
spoke Well, it was of course nice
выступал Ну так было Конечно приятно
In short, from Zelensky to hear the words that
Короче от Зеленского услышать слова что
the Dagestanis are there and he mentioned us,
дагестанцы там и он упомянул нас
the Circassians, he didn't
черкесов не
forget the Circassian says and so it was
забыл черкес говорит и так это было
nice he didn't
приятно он нас не
forget us in Ukraine at all and he
забыл какой-то там в Украине вообще и он
spoke for the Circassians in short  it was very
сказал за черкесов короче это было очень
nice In short, I have a cousin in Ukraine,
приятно Короче у меня у меня в Украине
maybe he  It turns out that I am
двоюродный брат жет он Получается я
half Circassian half Estonian and
наполовину черкес наполовину эстонец а
he is half Circassian half Ukrainian,
он наполовину черкес наполовину украинца
so he sent me this T-shirt and he
то он мне прислал эту футболку вот и он
says that the Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine
говорит что Верховная Рада Украины
recognized the genocide of the Circassian in the Russian
признала геноцид черкеса в Российской
Empire, yes, well, I know that Georgia is the
империи да Ну я знаю что Грузия вот
only one that recognized it, Georgia too
признала единствен Грузия тоже
and Ukraine But what about Ukraine  - I
и Украина А вот насчёт Украины что-то
heard from ours, in short, well, I do
слышал от наших короче ну Конкретно что
nt know specifically what they recognized. So, you know,
признали не знаю Так что и знаешь что
like ours, uh, it turns out that
как бы у наших ээ ещё вот получается
our grandfathers still knew their language. It
наши деды они ещё язык свой знали я вот
turns out that our father, uh, arrived in
получается у нас отец э приехал когда в
Estonia when I was already Estonian. He was 3.
Эстонию Я уже эстонский он ему было 3
years I he died it turns out and I was already growing up I
года я он погиб получается и я уже рос я
didn't hear the Circassian language at home and I
черкесского языка не слышал дома а я
only heard Estonian and Russian and Well
эстонский и русский только слышал и Ну
you look like Circassians our Circassians they are
ты похож на черкесы наши черкесы они
small In short all the clans are stocky like that
мелкие Короче все рода коренастые такие
Kabardins they are healthy in short here is the
кабардинцы они здоровые короче вот
Kabardin clan in short well tribe Uh-huh
кабардинский род короче ну племя Угу
they are Adyghe  thin but tall and the Circassians
адыгейцы они худые но высокие а черкесы
are small In short, everything is so yes And you
они мелкие Короче все так что да Во и
know, it turns out look at the whole
знаешь получается смотри вся
historical Land of the Circassians  this is all
историческая Земля черкесов это всё вот
this coast of Krasnodar these are the
это побережье Краснодара это ж
richest
богатейшие
territories Yes and
эти территории Да а они
now they are pouring fuel oil on our
сейчас мазутом заливают мазутом наши
ancestral lands Yes and they
предков ские земли Да ещё
even organized the Olympics in Krasnaya Polyana
и на Красной Поляне Олимпиаду
Krasnaya Polyana Yes
устроили Красная Поляна Да историческая
our historical Circassians rebelled In short, they were not
наши черкесы взбунтовались Короче их не
listened to by everyone quickly all the
послушали всех быстро все
same for the Krasnaya Polyana Olympics and  in
жа зате Красную поляну Олимпиада и вс
short, this is Krasnaya Polyana,
короче это Красная Поляна у нел там
our ancestors died there, there was the last
погибли наши предки там была последняя
battle.
битва
And look, they do it on purpose, to
А смотри Они специально делать так чтобы
mock, you know, to mock
надругаться понимаешь надругаться над
all of this. Yes, Yermola
этим всем Да ермола вот там
elevated
возвысил у себя
these houses there.
этих дома
And
Да и
women.
женщин
Yes, there, not only women. Even
Да да там что не только женщин Да даже
take  the same
взять ту же
Chechnya they say everywhere that how the
Чечню везде говорят что как издевались
Chechens mocked them And when the Russians went there
чеченцы А когда русские туда заходили
What did they do like this And Colonel
Они что делали так а полковник
Buda was generally happy about it He said
буда вобще ещ радовался этим говорил
there is footage I also have my brothers in
есть кадры у меня ещ у братьев есть
short and
короче да
five-year-olds Why is this video not posted
пятилетних почему это не выставляется
and only posted as Chechens
видео а выставляется только как чеченцы
in short For  What are
короче За что За
they putting up for that?  as if the
то они выставляют так как будто это
gangsters are good
банди хороши
for the cause, this is the cause, they are for their own on their own
за дело это дела они за сво на своей
land, they are for their children,
земле они за своих детей
who this is something that is not shown in the
которых это вот что-то не показывается в
video and all this is encrypted, everything is deleted.
видео и всё это всё шифруют всё удаляют
Well, how many videos do the Chechens have, the
Ну сколько видео есть у чеченцев у у ой
Nakhs still have these
нахов остались эти
videos  Why are you silent, but just a little
видео Почему молчите ато чуть-чуть
something, the word video there, he threw it
что-то слово видео там кинул короче
somewhere, in short, he quickly
куда-то он уже всё быстренько его
removes this
убирает этого
person because he
человека потому что
only wore a
носил только
Chechen, the same propaganda is going on
чечен такая же Пропаганда идёт
like the Nazis in Ukraine, and in Russia, what about
как в Украине нацисты А в России что ли
their pogroms,
их с погромы
things with them, yes  they write that it's like only
дела с ними да пишут что типа это только
Slavs can rent it out No, I'm not in Tyumen I
славянам сдавать Да не я вот в Тюмень я
myself, well, I've been in Russia my whole life, in short, I grew up
сам э ну всю жизнь в России короче вырос
in Yamal I
Я на Ямале
was born in the north, in short, I came to
родился на севере короче приехал в
Tyumen I moved to Tyumen I wanted to
Тюмень переехал в Тюмень я хотел
rent an apartment,
квартиру снять
well, I had to say I say I'm a
э мне пришлось сказать Я говорю я
Tatar I'm not  ska I didn't say that I'm a
татарин я не ска Я не сказал что я там
Caucasian there, a Circassian there, I say I'm a
кавказец там черкес там я говорю я
Tatar Well, Tatars are like ours Well, okay,
татарин А ну татары типа наш Ну ладно
like, more or less Russians In short, that's it,
типа ну более-менее россияне Короче всё
I arrived with a beard  She looks at me like this with
я приехал с бородой на меня вот так
her beard there, that's still a Small
смотрит бородой там ту это ещё Маленькая
breed like that
порода такая
Well, at least I didn't disgrace my
была Ну ничего зато я не посрамил свою
honor and my dignity In short, when I was
честь и своё достоинство Короче я когда
evicting her from there,
выселял оттудова
this woman surprised me that it was so
эта женщина удивила что там такая
clean and everything was done there and
чистота и там было Всё сделано и там
everything was cleaned and everything was washed  because
было всё убрано и всё вымыто потому что
we are Circassians very clean
мы черкес очень чистоплотный
She was surprised says I have says
Она удивилась говорит у меня говорит
girls lived here women lived but such
девушки здесь жили женщины жили но такой
says there was no cleanliness She was
говорит чистоты не было Она
surprised I say because I say we are
удивилась Я говорю потому что говорю мы
Circassians and therefore we
черкесы и поэтому мы
Well we are very clean
Ну мы очень чистоплотные
And so she she was very
И вот она она очень
surprised Well you see they compare us with
удивилась Ну видишь нас сравнивают с
Tajiks
таджиками
SBE with a beard means everything is back and forth in
сбе с бородой значит всё туда-сюда
short
короче
There and so on yes I agree with this that
Там и так далее да я согласен с этим что
yes I talked with Tajiks Yes
да с таджиками общался Да
they are
они
very
очень
in short like Muslims well Muslims as
короче вроде муслимы ну мусульмане как
if
бы
well they have dirt in their houses dirt
ну грязь у них у них дома грязь
in short with this Yes I agree and from  -for them
короче с этим Да я согласен и из-за них
they compare already, well, everyone, in short, who has a
сравнивают уже ну всех короче кто с
beard and who is not Russian, in short, and I
бородой и кто не русский короче и я
think so,
думаю так короче
in short, Yes, its sad that
Да печально во эти все выходит что
now everyone who speaks Russian Yes,
сейчас все кто говорят по-русски Да уже
they are already being recorded as Russian, where from  there are 100
их записывают в русский откуда там 100
million Russians Yes, the Mari are now Russians The
млн русских Да марийцы теперь русские
Chuvash are now Russians Tatars Russians
Чуваши теперь русские татары русские
Yuri Gagarin, what
Юрий Гагарин кто по
nationality was he, in my opinion, either a Mari or a
нации по-моему он был или мариец или
Veps, something like that, a
вепс что-то такое чуваш
pure Chuvash, a pure-blooded Chuvash Well, for some reason, the
чистой чисто кровный чуваш Ну почему-то
first Russian to fly into space
русский первый в космос полетел чисто
was a pure-blooded Chuvash  bloody Well,
кровный чуваш был чисто кровный Да ну
they wrote it Russian Russian flew into
его написали русский русский полетел в
space st. Excuse me Look what a smart
космос ул Извини меня Смотри какой умный
man Was found among the Chuvash That he was the first
человек Нашёлся среди чувашей Что первым
into space and not so not a rope he is Russian
в космос а не так не канат он русский
so they are now look when over the river
так они сейчас смотри когда вот над рек
Stam who put up the flag Kazakh and
стам кто поставил знамя казах и
Georgian how are they now they  they have
грузин как они сейчас они убрали они
now removed all the Russians, uh, there was a Kazakh,
теперь всё русские э был э казах
uh, he put his shoulder so that the Kazakh and the Tatar, the
ээ плечо поставил чтобы казах и татарин
Tatar climbed in and put the Kazakh, he
татарин залез и поставил казах ему
put the Tatar and the Kazakh And now they have
поставил татарин и казах А у них сейчас
everything
всё
Russian, Russian and Georgian because
русский русский и грузин потому что
Stalin is Georgian and Well, that is, and Russian
Сталин грузин и Ну то есть и русского
She was In short, put it out  Georgians and
Она была Короче это выставить грузины и
Russians,
русский
and who is really above them,
а который вот им реально над рего
who is the main one?  They put up a banner,
который вот этот главный Знамя поставили
it was a Kazakh and a Tatar, they broke through
это был казах и татарин они прорвались
there, but their history, in short, I
туда Но их по по истории Короче там я
read a lot of materials, well,
очень многие материалы читал ну
their classified ones,
засекреченные их
then, in my opinion, something
потом по-моему что-то вообще короче их
was made from them, in short, everything was like that in the
из них сделали Там короче так всё в
Soviet Union, yes, everything was like that in the Soviet Union  they
Советском Союзе Да в Советском Союзе все
didn't disclose in short
не раскрывали короче
Yes, that's how it was with a Russian Georgian
Да так оно было сде русский грузин
who had nothing to do with it at all, there is
который вообще к этому отношения вообще
such a thing
имели есть такое
Yes, so I also talked to Ukrainians
Да так что я н с украинцами тоже общался
and asked, I'm half Circassian and
да спрашивал я вот наполовину черкес
half Estonian Yes, most of them
наполовину эстонец Да они большинство
know who Circassians are, they only
знают кто такие черкесы единственно
ask like I'm from  aga say or from
спрашивают типа я из аге говорят или из
di balkari yes I say that my family is from
ди балкари да я говорю что Мой род из
Krasnodar region that Circassia was
Краснодарского края что Черкесия была
bigger yes now Lenin specially
больше да сейчас нас специально Ленин
drew us like this so that the communists
нарисовал вот так чтоб коммунисты
made Adygea Kabardina Balkaria
сделали Адыгея кабардина Балкария
Karachay Circassia broke broke
карачаева Черкесия разбили разбили
broke it then
разбили его тогда
yes
да
Mixed specially so that we would not unite
Смешали специально чтобы мы не соединили
now even with our  they don't even let Putin
сейчас даже нашим уже не дают даже Путин
return, in short, from Turkey, in
не даёт вернуться короче с Турции в
Turkey, in short, there are
Турции короче
somewhere around 7-8
где-то 7-8
million, in Turkey, only 7-8 million, the
млн в Турции только 7-8 млн самая
strongest  diaspora Now ours in short
сильная диаспора Сейчас наша короче в
is in Turkey Jordan Syria in short and
Турции находится Иордания Сирия короче и
also in Germany our diaspora there well well you
также в Германии наша диаспора там ну ну
know for me for me there is always this
знаешь для меня для меня всегда есть вот
This is an example How the Jews Yes 2,000 years
Это пример Как евреи Да 2.000 лет не
were not on their own land and were able to
были на своей вот этой земле и смогли
create a state And it seems to me
сделать государство Да и мне кажется
the Circassians  they can too,
черкесы тоже смогут вот
but they remember that they are Circassians while they
по они помнят что они черкесы пока они у
keep it in their souls and
себя в душе это держат и детям
tell their children that you are Circassian. This is your
рассказывают что вы черкес Вот это ваша
homeland, this is what is rightfully yours.
Родина это то что вам надлежит по праву
Yes, today it is impossible. Tomorrow it may be
Да сегодня это невозможно Завтра может
impossible. And the day after tomorrow everything will change.
невозможно А послезавтра всё изменится
And like Israel, for example.  they are Jews from
Да и как например Израиль они евреи со
all over the world Yes, they started going there and
всего мира Да начали ехать туда и
made their own state, they got
сделали сво государство вернули
back the Circassians and Jews, what's the difference, they
себе черкесов и евреев в чём разница они
know how to
умеют
cheat, they are very clever at cheating, and the Circassians,
хитрить они Очень умно хитрят а черкесы
what do we have, we have an Adyghe hub We always
что у нас у нас адыга хаб Мы всегда
only directly, in short, on Maybe this is not a
только напрямую короче на Может это не
mistake, but this is  it's fair
ошибка Но это зато это справедливо
In short, if a Circassian gave his word He
Короче если черкес слово дал Он своё
keeps his word We even we Circassians keep our word more
слово держит Мы даже мы черке сво слово
strongly even all our word there
держим сильнее даже все сво слово там
Dagestan  no Circassian keeps his
Дагестан нет черкес держит сильнее своё
word stronger because we still observe Adyghe
слово потому что мы ещё соблюдаем адыга
khaby we are the only people who
хабы мы единственный народ Который
observe ahab Well that is, honor our
соблюдает ахаб Ну то есть честь свою
laws and so on In short
законах и так далее Короче
we We are also
мы Мы также
called the French of the Caucasus we
называемся французами Кавказа мы моду
gave fashion to all Caucasian
дали всему кавказскому
people Circassian is ours Gazyri are ours
народу черке это наше газыри - это наши
all Caucasian  the peoples made it public and
все кавказские народы это обнародовали и
they put it on because
они это одели потому что
it was military in short, well, it was
это это воинская короче ну нам было
convenient for us to fight in it, our ancestors
удобно в этом воевать нашим предкам
in short, and also the same Chechens. Old
короче и также те же чеченцы Старые
Chechens know who the Circassians are and they do
чеченцы знают ккто такие черкесы и они
nt even argue and we, the Chechens, we
даже не спорят и мы чеченцев же мы
Circassians call them younger brothers. Although the
черкесы называем младшими братьями Хотя
Chechens  now they are arising in short but the
чеченцы сейчас возникают короче но
Old Chechens they agree with this
Старые чеченцы они с этим соглашаются
that they are our younger ones bya
что они наши младшие бя
that's why we are the only people we are
вот поэтому мы единственный народ мы
Circassians Adyghe who still observe ahab
черкесы Адыги которые ещё соблюдаем ахаб
and we have respect for elders we have
и у нас есть уважение к старшим у нас
respect for younger people respect for women and
уважение к младшим уважение к женщинам и
so on We are not like the Chechens  or
так далее Мы не такие как чеченцы или
there Dagestanis we are a completely different people
там дагестанцы мы совсем другой Народ у
our people are completely different  attitude towards
нас совсем другое отношение к
women but nobody knows us we
женщинам но нас никто не знает мы
say that we are Circassians like that
говорим что мы черкесы такие
I say I am Kabardian and we
Я говорю я кабардинец а кабардинцев мы
know Kabardians that is they destroyed us our history
знаем то есть нас так нашу историю
that it is offensive In short
что обидно Короче
yes well I say as you know we ourselves are
да ну я говорю как знаешь мы и сами
many but I don't know I forgot Well I  no
многие вот я не знаю я забыл Ну я без
father Father died at an early age I don't
отца Отец умер в раннем возрасте Я не
know my Circassian Well, our language is
знаю свой Черкесский аы Ну у нас язык-то
Adyghe Abkhazian our close brothers are
адыга абхазский наши близки братья это
Abkhazians I don't know my language a couple of words
абхазы Я не знаю свой язык пару слов
too I can exchange I speak like that
тоже так могу перекинуться я так
in Karachay in short in any
разговариваю на Карачай короче на любом
Turkic But Adyghe is the same  one of the
тюркском Но адыгский он же самый один из
most difficult languages like
самых сложнейших языков как типа
Japanese Chinese in my opinion
японского китайского по-моему
I don't know my language and even in our
вот я не знаю свой язык и у нас даже в
songs now they sing that we Circassians we are
песнях сейчас уже поётся что мы черке мы
forgetting our language and we don't even
забываем свой язык и мы его даже не
know it they destroyed us as a
знаем уничтожили как
people how can we continue our language
народ как мы можем дальше свой язык
there is no way to develop it And now there are 10 million more people in the
никак И сейчас миллионов 10 в
world than we have in Estonia, there is a
мире больше чем у нас в Эстонии там пол
population of half a million at most You see, they have
милна населения от силы Понимаешь есть
their own country And it turns out that the Adyghe don't have
своя страна А у адыгов получается нет
their own country
своей страны у
cherkessov Yes on ae there Kabardina Balkaria
черкесов Да на ае там кабардина Балкария
in short cherkes something like that divided
короча черкес что-то так разделили
in short artificial and even those same now
короче искусственное и Даже те же сейчас
young who grew up in Kabarda he says I am a
молодые Кто в Кабарде вырос он говорит я
Kabardian I say how can you be a
кабардинец я говорю ты как можешь быть
Kabardian you say cherkes you are a dyk no
кабардинцев ты говорю черкес ты адык нет
I am a Kabardian well with a tomboy here in
я кабардинец ну с пацанкой здесь в
In Tyumen he met an 18 year old boy and an
Тюмене встретился ему 18 лет пацанёнок о
adult man
взрослый как-то мужчина
somehow so I say I am a Circassian I say he says
так я говорю я черкесс говорю он говорит
and I am a Kabardian I say So we are
а я кабардинец я говорю Так мы и есть
Circassians No I say Kabardian I am not a
черкесы Нет я говорит кабардинец я не
Circassian You see how they divided Yes
черкес Вот видишь как разделили Да
they made different Republics for one
сделали разные Республики для одного
people and called them  differently
народа и назвали по-другому
Well yes Well so they artificially
Ну да Ну так нас искусственно
separated us so that we would all
разделились чтобы мы короче вместе все
come together in short We wouldn't come together And then it continues in
сошлись Да и дальше это продолжается
short and we can't return my
короче и мы не можем вернуться мои
ancestors can't return to their icon
предки не могут вернуться на свою икону
in the ground and we are damned because they are afraid of the
в землю и нам адым потому что они боятся
Russians what if we return  There are
русские что мы если вернёмся все нас
about 10 million of us and we will make our own Adyghe
около 10 млн и мы сделаем свой адыга
abzy That is, Zhenya has elders  Zhenya to
абзы То есть у Женя к старшим у Женя к
relatives Zhenya and so on In short
близким у Женя ну и так далее Короче
honor is not afraid of this Because forgive
честь не боятся этого Потому что извини
me 10 million if to return We are ours
меня 10 млн если возвратиться Мы же своё
I can say than
я можем сказать чем
Russian Russians
русский русские
they threw off the bone they hid it
они кость скинули они и с ховали её
In short everything
Короче всё
and we have honor we can what  -to
а у нас есть честь мы можем что-то
say but there are few of us only in
сказать но нас мало нас всего лишь в
Russia there are maximum of up to
России там осталось максимум Ну до
100,000 left and even then they are all
100000 всего лишь и то все
scattered and they don't let us
раскиданы и нам не дают сюда
return here And we even know our
вернуться А мы даже знаем на адыга наш
Adyghe language in Adyghe - this is the
адыгский язык - это язык
Ngari language I heard such a language Ngari Gari
нгари слышал такой язык нгари гарский
yes it is a language  humane no
да это язык человечный
one knows it it's not even
его никто не знает это даже не
taught there in universities and so
преподается там в университетах и так
on In short because well it's not
далее Короче потому что ну это не
profitable but the Adyghe know the old
выгодно вот а Адыги знают старые
Adyghe the Ngari language it was the language of
Адыги язык нгари это язык был
humanity And these here they are
человечности Вот и вот эти вот они
afraid of the language of humanity Because
боятся языка человечности Потому что
if we speak the language
если мы заговори на языке
we will rise up to humanity
человечности мы воспр восстанем
because
бо
then they know that the Adyghe are the only
да потом что они знают что Адыги только
Adyghe left who
Адыги остались которые ещё
still observe the culture and hospitality.
ну культуру го гостеприимство ещё до сих
Until now.  it's hard but
пор соблюдают До сих пор тяжело но
they observe it although it's broken
соблюдают хотя её ломают
everywhere only the Adyghe
везде только Адыги
still have abzy and they have nokh cheva nokh cheva they
ещ абзы а у них нох чева нох чева они
don't know their nokh cheva anymore and the Circassians
нох чева свою уже не знают а черкесы
know what ady abzy is every Circassian
знают что такое ады абзы каждый черкес
knows it but not everyone of course observes it
это знает но не каждый конечно соблюдает
and the Chechens don't even know their nokh cheva
а чеченцы даже ног чева свою не
But  Everyone knows the Chechens, but
знают Зато чеченцев все знают а черкесов
no one knows the Circassians. The Circassians fought with the Russians for
никого никто не знает черкесы с русскими
over 100 years, I
больше 100 лет воевали
think
э по-моему
three. They fought for centuries, but history
три ри Столетия они воевали просто это
keeps silent about it.
умалчивает по
That's how it is, my fellow countryman. Okay,
истории Вот такие дела земляк да Хорошо
good luck to
давай удачи
you. Write to my Telegram right now.
тебе пись на мий Telegram прямо зараз
Axis VN
ось ВН
apoc tse very  and it is very important YouTube Zaga
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube Зага
us through scarg ORV in your ban and very
нас через скарг ОРВ в твый бан и дуже
many videos I do not show to people at times I do not
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams That is
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
why we Mali operational links
того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок
are written right now and while there  in telegra
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okrim video also
окрим видео ще теж
interesting and useful information and we are obliged
цикава и корисна информация и мы повинни
to you to trim the current operational
з вами тримати постийний оперативный
connection
звязок
independently in that will show you the process
незалежно в того чи покаже вам проце
YouTube Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
write L
пиши L